[SPEAKER_01]: Why ill-will and lust, exactly?
[SPEAKER_05]: Why do they always go hand in hand?
[SPEAKER_05]: Why, when there is lust, there will be ill-will?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, when there's a dependency on lust, which is always directed towards things in the world, with that comes the possibility that other people might get in your way.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, but even more acutely, from your point of view, so, that dependency on lust, how is that maintained?
[SPEAKER_05]: How do you perpetuate your own dependency on lust?
[SPEAKER_05]: By being lustful.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, but how are you being lustful?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, by not seeing the danger in being lustful, by not knowing the escape from that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, so a person doesn't know the escape, but can find the escape, by not doing certain things, which, if you're doing, you're keeping your dependence on lust.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what are those things that you should talk about, that you shouldn't do, while you're still dependent on lust?
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, what you should not do is attend to things that are provocative of lust.
[SPEAKER_05]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, okay, virtue, sense, strength, but then you should not be grasping the features of beautiful that are increasing the lust, increasing the wanting, increasing the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it's because
[SPEAKER_05]: If you, unchecked, are constantly grasping the features of beautiful, let your mind dwell on them, want them, delight in them, welcome them, you will be unable to help yourself but grasp the features of ugly, when you experience the disagreeable experience.
[SPEAKER_05]: In other words, you will be grasping the features of hate.
[SPEAKER_05]: When the experience changes.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, if you meet somebody who is not a lovely person and who is quite unpleasant, your mind will not be able to not pick the features of resistance to that and anger and everything else that will come out of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's operating on the level of science.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because the mind operates on picking up the features.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: It has not discerned the bigger picture and learned how not to pick the features and signs and features of beautiful.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, there will be signs and features of beautiful waiting, but you don't need to pick them up.
[SPEAKER_05]: But you can't not pick them up, because all you know is acting towards sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: Same.
[SPEAKER_05]: There will be features of ugly and unpleasant, but you can't not pick them up and get all wound up and angry, because you keep acting towards sense objects.
[SPEAKER_05]: But you're not angry.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you can wish, or if I cannot get angry now, well, you can achieve that by not being sensual either when you're not angry.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you haven't understood it correctly, you will still be blaming that on the situation not being good enough.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's what sensuality means.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's what the ill-will means.
[SPEAKER_05]: It means seeing past where the problem actually is and assuming it on the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_05]: The last, the delight, the gratification is not in the sense of objects.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's in your happiness and delight on account of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: But you see way, way past that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Immediately, you're down into the objects.
[SPEAKER_05]: Equally, when it's unpleasant, the pain, the discomfort of it, it's not because of some hateful word you're experiencing and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's because your mind's resisting it.
[SPEAKER_05]: But you don't see that level.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're way past it, onto the face of the person that's annoying you.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, through cultivating sensuality, not practicing sense restraint, you are cultivating your mind of overlooking where the problem is, not seeing that domain.
[SPEAKER_05]: That is all there is to it.
[SPEAKER_05]: But in order to see that level, in order to be able to recognize it, endure it sufficiently until you see your intentions in regard to it,
[SPEAKER_05]: You have to have, out of faith or some sort of pondering and understanding, withdrawn yourself from acting out towards sense objects, beautiful or ugly.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, precepts.
[SPEAKER_05]: Acting towards sensuality, acting out of anger, ill-will, hatred, bad speech, all of that needs to have been honed in and restrained.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, in other words, it's impossible to not
[SPEAKER_05]: To be able to not grasp the signs and features and overlook where the problem is in regard to sensuality or real will, if you're still not withdrawn from it with your body, if you're still acting out and seeking.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's called things that entail suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: Dukkha dhamma.
[SPEAKER_03]: Dukkha dhammas.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's got like a few questions, which we can stop at and see.
[SPEAKER_03]: It says, when a bhikkhu completely understands the comings and goings, as I just translated that origin and cessation, when he completely understands the comings and goings of things that entail suffering, then sensual pleasures have been seen by him in such a way that as he looks at them,
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, he has comprehended a way of living whereby evil unwholesome states of greed, lust and sadness or displeasure do not flow in upon him.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's the first statement, and it's just broken up into a few parts.
[SPEAKER_03]: The first question is, and how does a bhikkhu completely understand the comings and goings of things that entail suffering?
[SPEAKER_03]: How is that understood?
[SPEAKER_03]: Any ideas?
[SPEAKER_02]: Comings and goings is that
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not a trick question.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I know, but I'm wondering...
[SPEAKER_02]: Rising and falling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Upādāvaya.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, just how it's... And the translation is like how it's produced and how it falls apart, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you... How do you know that?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you understand that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, to endure, without interfering or acting out of them.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's one, and I would say, it doesn't really say it there, but it does say, such is form.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I was going to say, what are the things that entail suffering?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, this is form.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is its origin.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is its cessation.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, to me, that's saying... And how does he understand things?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, he investigates it.
[SPEAKER_05]: The problem there is, though, that one can investigate and get the right answers, but still on the abstract level.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, yeah, such is form.
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, the whole commentarial texts were written on what the form is.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's made up of this.
[SPEAKER_05]: Made up of that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, I got information thus this is the form.
[SPEAKER_05]: But no, it starts with endurance.
[SPEAKER_05]: By not acting out of the form that pressures you, not acting out of the concern in regard to your form that you are pressured by, by discerning the nature of it enduring there, on its own, you're paired with it, then you get to see such is the form.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, you might not know,
[SPEAKER_05]: You have the information how the form came about, and you don't need to.
[SPEAKER_05]: You can still understand the aggregate of form.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, but having it endure, you know, such is form, and then you start to let it, well, you let it endure, then you get to see all these other... Yeah, but that needs to be qualified, because, as I said, people already think they can practice the dhamma without a right view, means they can think that all this information you get and you learn about the first, second, fourth jhāna, the five aggregates, all of that applies to them already, but it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_05]: In order for it to apply, you need to create a basis for which to apply.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's the basis.
[SPEAKER_05]: Precepts, guiding of the sense doors, the mind, purification, development on account of it, and then, yeah, such is the form that endures.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because, see, even people, they would then be finding out what is the form, where it comes from, why is it here, how is it here, what created it, what will be its end.
[SPEAKER_05]: All of those questions,
[SPEAKER_05]: would be rooted in trying to get rid of the form.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, they don't understand what form is, because they don't want to endure it, because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_05]: The pressure is uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, I'm practicing the dhamma just to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, the understanding begins by not acting out on that level.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then you will know what form is.
[SPEAKER_05]: Form is there.
[SPEAKER_05]: And as it says in other suttas, he doesn't care whether it's far or near, personal, impersonal, up, down, left, right, past, future.
[SPEAKER_05]: He knows the aggregator form as aggregator form.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's all I need to know.
[SPEAKER_05]: Within that, then, you can actually understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's how form is.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's how it increases.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's how it decreases.
[SPEAKER_05]: The entire extent of it has been abandoned by me because I'm not acting out of it anymore.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm not trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm not seeking the pleasure through it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, same goes for the feeling, perception, intentions and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can get all that information, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, the result should be
[SPEAKER_03]: That when sensual pleasures
[SPEAKER_03]: When there are sensual pleasures available, he should have no desire.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: There, there's an infatuation for it, because he's understood the form, he's understood the feeling, so...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you've got all this information, a vast amount of it, but there's still that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, that should be an indication that you've... you just have information that's... that doesn't apply to you.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not applying it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not seeing it rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't understand it without seeing... without seeing the escape from it, basically, or without having the passion in regard to its... diminish or not... not being able to... at the same time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Very incompatible.
[SPEAKER_03]: Vipassana, gratification, danger, escape.
[SPEAKER_03]: And how are sensual pleasures seen by him in such a way that as he looks at them, sensual desire does not lie latent within him?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how are sensual pleasures seen?
[SPEAKER_04]: As impermanent.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why they are unsatisfying.
[SPEAKER_04]: They don't last.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, he sees them as unsatisfying, impermanent unsatisfaction, but also...
[SPEAKER_05]: Ugly.
[SPEAKER_05]: You've got to be seeing them as actually not attractive.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, as I said before many times, you won't see that if your only concern is to act out towards more pleasure or get rid of the pain of not acting out towards pleasure.
[SPEAKER_05]: I must replace this with a subha, subha, subha, because subha bothers me too much.
[SPEAKER_05]: While you're looking at subha, as the sutta says, while you're looking at the beautiful, while he sees it, he is not attracted to it anymore.
[SPEAKER_05]: There is no underlying desire and lust that can overwhelm the mind.
[SPEAKER_05]: Why?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because while he sees it, he sees the ugly within it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because that's what truly is.
[SPEAKER_05]: If it weren't so, freedom from sensuality would not be possible, nor sensuality would be a problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: But sensuality is a problem because it's a contradiction, it's a bait, it's a trap.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it's not understood.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not understood for what it really is.
[SPEAKER_05]: And why it's not understood for what it really is?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because the mind is so used to, and has been doing it for so long, just picks the beautiful.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, imagine you have a bowl of just food and rubbish and dirt, everything just mixed in it, with some pieces that actually taste nice.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it's all part of the same mix.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, that's sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: Just focusing on the bits that taste nice and ignoring where it comes from and what it remains while you're eating it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you have to stop ignoring it while it is there.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's why I keep saying, you can't just... yes, you have to be restrained and not just carelessly engage with thoughts of sensuality, but at the same time, you have to recognize that those thoughts are real as such, pressures are real as such, attraction is real as such, and you have to stop acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And one way of acting out of it is trying to replace it with a subha or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, you need to understand it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you will not see what lies at the other end of subha, if you're too preoccupied in trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Try directing out towards it, and get, you know, free from that pressure that imposes over you, or, eh... distracting yourself with other thoughts, just so that... until this disappears, because you can't deal with it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Precepts are there to protect you, so you don't actually... if you can't deal with it mentally, so you don't act out, okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: Endure the pressure of the pull, so that next time you see something that used to pull you, there will be no underlying tendency, like basically waiting to pounce on you, because you actually saw it as ugly, as unwanted.
[SPEAKER_05]: You saw it as burning embers.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's the... so yeah, he's...
[SPEAKER_03]: Concentrate, concentrate, concentrate, concentrate.
[SPEAKER_05]: Ah, super, super, super.
[SPEAKER_05]: Why?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because you don't want to deal with the pain.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because there's no problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: You haven't acted out.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're obviously not wanting it mentally.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you're not delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what's the problem then?
[SPEAKER_05]: Why can't you bear that pain?
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, because you don't want pain.
[SPEAKER_05]: Which means, by proxy, you still want pleasure.
[SPEAKER_05]: Just not this anymore, sure.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, for as long as you try to, as we said before, as long as you're trying to get rid of the pain, and replace it with pleasure, you will want to have pleasure and not have pain.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thus, you're still very much within sensual domain, on account of you trying to overcome your sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, don't act out, don't delight in it, but then, when seen, when thought of, see through it, not at the expense of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, see, and as this simile says, see the danger in it, you know, suppose...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how does he see, look at sensual pleasures or beauty?
[SPEAKER_03]: Suppose there is a charcoal pit deeper than a man's height, filled with glowing coals.
[SPEAKER_03]: A man would come along, wanting to live, not wanting to die, desiring happiness and averse to suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then two strong men would grab him by both arms and drag him towards that charcoal pit.
[SPEAKER_03]: The man would wriggle his body this way and that.
[SPEAKER_03]: For what reason?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because he knows, I will fall into this charcoal pit and I will thereby meet death or deadly suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it is dangerous, this thing that's beautiful.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, ironically enough, when people try to get rid of these sensual perceptions, they're trying to get rid of the pain of recognizing the charcoal pit in them.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's what they're trying to get rid of.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, asubha, asubha, concentrate, don't think about, don't think about, remove the thoughts, remove the thoughts, remove the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's basically just stop showing me the pain of the charcoal pit, because I can't bear it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Why?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because it's still very painful.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, this thing is painful.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if I go in this direction, that is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_05]: Leave that pain of the pressure.
[SPEAKER_05]: Don't act out by body, by speech.
[SPEAKER_05]: Don't mentally proliferate further.
[SPEAKER_05]: But then, thoughts that are there, that are pressuring you, painful, that's what you train in regard to.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, you realize, oh, yeah, this pain, I'm just habitually trying to sort of evade.
No.
[SPEAKER_05]: That is the pain of these things.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I'm not there now.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because I've already been withdrawn by not acting towards.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now, I just needed to stop resisting that pain to see where that pain truly belongs.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not to me.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not because of my sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not because of mine.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's because that's what sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_05]: A charcoal pit.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, you won't have to be restraining yourself anymore, because you wouldn't want to go into a charcoal pit.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, seeing the danger...
[SPEAKER_03]: And then how, from that point, how has a bhikkhu comprehended a way of living whereby evil, unwholesome states of greed and sadness or grief do not flow in upon him?
[SPEAKER_05]: How?
[SPEAKER_03]: What will be the way of living that he has discovered now, that will keep him safe?
[SPEAKER_05]: And make him cross to the other shore.
[SPEAKER_04]: A noble path.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, I was going to say, what else?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But what you said in the beginning is, well, heedfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Heedfulness, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Heedfulness in regard to the noble path.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, this is to how I should live now.
[SPEAKER_05]: Very careful.
[SPEAKER_05]: For my own welfare, which is what I always wanted.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's why I was seeking sensuality and safety and comfort and, you know, identity in the world.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's because I thought that was for my own welfare.
[SPEAKER_05]: I thought it was for my well-being.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now I recognize, no, that was all a trap.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: I still want the well-being of myself.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's still a valid thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: But now you recognize where that welfare truly is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it still remains you.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, the criteria remains, but now you go very differently about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the simile.
[SPEAKER_03]: Suppose a man would enter a thorny forest.
[SPEAKER_03]: There would be thorns in front of him, thorns behind, thorns to the left, thorns to the right, thorns below him, thorns above him.
[SPEAKER_03]: He would go forward mindfully.
[SPEAKER_03]: He would go back mindfully, thinking, may no thorn stab me.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, too, whatever in the world has a pleasing and agreeable nature is called a thorn in the noble one's discipline.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, don't stab yourself on it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and just... there is thorns.
[SPEAKER_03]: Be careful.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, having understood this way of living, one should then make... understand restraint and non-restraint.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: You should know the difference.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, okay, so now, how do I be careful in this?
[SPEAKER_05]: You understand the extent of restraint and what it leads to, and the extent of non-restraint and what it leads to.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not just an immediate, oh, I restrain, I don't restrain.
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: Life, a mode of being of restraint, leads away from this, and he understands it.
[SPEAKER_05]: He's not just taking it on faith to practice a restraint.
[SPEAKER_05]: He sees a direct result of restraint, and direct result of non-restraint.
[SPEAKER_05]: Simultaneously there, he sees it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it's not even a matter of choice by that point, what he will choose and do.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what does he understand?
[SPEAKER_03]: There's no restraint.
[SPEAKER_03]: Here, having...
[SPEAKER_03]: I've just translated a bit different.
[SPEAKER_03]: Here, having perceived an object with the senses, Bhikkhu is intent upon a pleasing form and repelled by a displeasing form.
[SPEAKER_03]: He lives without having set up recollection of the body, with a limited, narrow mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: And in that way, he does not know a liberated mind or a liberation through wisdom, whereby those evil, unwholesome states completely cease.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, he understands what restraint is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Restraint is not being intent upon.
[SPEAKER_03]: Restraint does not mean not having eyes and not seeing things.
[SPEAKER_05]: Restraint means... Understanding the restraint or non-restraint means understanding where the problem of lust and non-lust
[SPEAKER_05]: Where the problem of lust is.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it's in grasping the beautiful signs, not getting rid of the beautiful things in the world.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, if I keep attending to these signs that remain present, but I choose to then attend to them further, mind of lust will increase.
[SPEAKER_05]: And he fully understands that.
[SPEAKER_05]: The animal will go wilder.
[SPEAKER_05]: I attained it.
[SPEAKER_05]: It almost listens to me.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now I'm letting it go wild again.
[SPEAKER_05]: If I don't attend to these things that are still present there, I'm not trying to get rid of them either, but I simply don't attend to them, the animal will remain calm, and the mind will turn toward liberation, not toward lust.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it's directly seen and understood.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, so he lives in such a way, his restraint.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, occasionally, due to a lapse of memory, mindfulness, evil and wholesome intentions connected with the defilements arise in him.
[SPEAKER_03]: Slow might be the arising of his recollection and his remembering, but then he quickly abandons the spells and puts an end to them.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, even though it does arise again, you know, he is being mindful.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, see, he puts, he dispels, he gets rid of them, he puts an end to them.
[SPEAKER_05]: How?
[SPEAKER_05]: By slowly, slow arising of the context of the mindfulness, of what is peril, what is danger, what is sensory strength.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not by... he gets rid of them.
[SPEAKER_05]: He gets rid of them by thinking about something else.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: He gets rid of them by recreating
[SPEAKER_05]: Recollecting the bigger picture that he has discerned beforehand.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Basically, as the other simile in the Sutta says, like, you heat up a pan and as the drops of water fall, they will evaporate immediately if the pan is hot.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, he gets rid of them by heating the pan, not by catching the drops of water and preventing it from falling onto the pan.
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: Keep the pan hot.
[SPEAKER_05]: Nothing can stick to it.
[SPEAKER_05]: No water can soak it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, that's that's the samādhi, actually.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just as a man let two or three drops of water fall onto an iron plate, heated for a whole day, slow might be the falling of the drops of water, but then they would quickly vaporize and vanish.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's almost finished, yeah?
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus a bhikkhu has
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus Bhikkhu has comprehended a way of living whereby evil and wholesome states of greed and sadness do not flow in upon him.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when he is living in such a way, various other people might invite him to accept wealth.
[SPEAKER_03]: There might be some options available.
[SPEAKER_03]: Some praise, gain, fame.
[SPEAKER_03]: Come, good man, why let these robes weigh you down?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why roam about with a shaven head and a begging bowl?
[SPEAKER_03]: Come, having returned to the lower life, enjoy wealth and do notorious deeds.
[SPEAKER_03]: Indeed, when a bhikkhu is living in that way, it is impossible that he will give up the training and return to the lower life.
[SPEAKER_03]: The simile.
[SPEAKER_03]: Suppose that when the river Ganges slants and slopes and inclines towards the east,
[SPEAKER_03]: And a great crowd of people would come along, bringing a shovel and a basket, thinking, we will make this river Ganges slant and slope and incline towards the west.
[SPEAKER_03]: What do you think, Bhikkhus, would that great crowd of people be able to make the river Ganges slant, slope and incline towards the west?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, Venerable Sir.
[SPEAKER_03]: For what reason?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because the river Ganges slants, slopes and inclines towards the east, and it's not easy to make it slant and incline towards the west.
[SPEAKER_03]: That crowd, great crowd of people, would only reap fatigue and disappointment.
[SPEAKER_03]: Likewise, it is with the bhikkhu whose mind has for a long time slanted, sloped and inclined towards detachment or seclusion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus, it is impossible that he will give up the training and return to the low life.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's completely protected, really.
[SPEAKER_03]: No matter how many people or pressures, external possibilities, invitations,
[SPEAKER_03]: They'll just fall flat anyway.